Okay בוקר טוב. Boqer tov. Today's דף daf is נ"ו, Nun Vav,
56, and we pick up at the top on רבא לטעמיה, Rava
l'ta'amei, five lines down. Basically what we had been discussing was we
once again were revisiting the issue of what type of a you
know boundary would demarcate two separate fields for the הלכה halakha of
חזקה. chazaqah. That if you do חזקה chazaqah on one, it doesn't
work on the other. This would be by נכסי הגר, nikhsei ha-ger,
fields that are ownerless, because if somebody is selling them to you,
then the fact that you've paid for them would make it define
it as relating your חזקה chazaqah relating to both fields, or the
fact that somebody's trying to transfer to you could define your חזקה
chazaqah as relating to both fields according to one גמרא Gemara right
even if they're in completely separate locations. But if they're הפקר, hefker,
then the physical reality has to define itself as going on both.
So if there's a boundary line, a boundary marker, or some type
of a mound between them, or trees, or whatever, מפה, mapah, a
grass that is used to demarcate the boundary, what works on one
does not work on the other. And the question is what would
be in other areas of הלכה? halakha? So yesterday we explored פאה.
pe'ah. Do you give two separate corners or one corner on the
two fields? And טומאה, tum'ah, when there's a question about a doubtful
טומאה tum'ah in a private domain, according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
that's only if you definitely went into the field. But if you
don't know if you went into the field at all, then you
would be טהור. tahor. So is it defined as one field or
two fields? So there was a debate whether this type of a
boundary marker for those הלכות halakhot would define it as one field
or two. And then the גמרא Gemara ended up by saying that
when it comes to שבת, Shabbos, it would definitely be one field,
but רבא Rava would consider it two. So what is the relevance
for that? You know, why don't we just pick up with that
again? We'll repeat what we did at the end of yesterday. So
let's pick up at the bottom of נ"ה עמוד ב'. Nun Hei
amud beis. So the גמרא Gemara says five lines from the bottom,
אבל לשבת לא. aval l'Shabbos lo. For שבת Shabbos purposes, this boundary
marker would not define it as two fields. רבא אמר אפילו לענין
שבת. Rava amar afilu l'inyan Shabbos. Even when it comes to שבת,
Shabbos, it would be two. Now what is the relevance for שבת?
Shabbos? So we're going to see it's not about fields, it's about
some type of a division of a רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, of
a public domain. דתניא, De-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, beraisa, הוציא
חצי גרוגרת לרשות הרבים, hotzi chatzi grogeres l'reshus harabim,
you took out half of a pressed fig, meaning the quantity, the
volume of a half a pressed fig, because for שבת Shabbos you
only transgress, there has to be a minimum size, so only when
the thing you carry, if it's food, is the size of a
pressed fig. So you carried out half that amount into a public
domain from a private to a public domain, והניחה, ve-hinnichah, and you
put it down, וחזר והוציא חצי גרוגרת אחרת, ve-chazar ve-hotzi chatzi grogeres
acheres,
and you then did another one. Okay, so do those two acts
combine to be one act? Right, like for example, when you're eating
something that is forbidden, what defines that it's one act is that
it takes place, you know, תוך כדי אכילת פרס, tokh kedei akhilas
pras, the time it takes to eat half a loaf of bread,
and if you eat them more distant from one another, right, then
they're two separate acts and they don't combine. And so if you
did a half here and a half two hours later, you haven't
transgressed. So here you don't have the time period per se, but
it's העלם אחד, he'elam echad, one state of having forgotten. You didn't
remember in between that it was שבת. Shabbos. Because here the question
is you're doing it unintentionally, and do they combine to obligate you
to bring a קרבן חטאת. korban chattas. So if it's one state
of forgetting, you haven't remembered in between, those combine and it's like
you've done one full act of carrying. חייב. Chayav. בשני העלמות פטור.
Bi-shnei he'elamos patur.
But if there's two acts of forgetting, because in the middle, 'Oh
my God, it was שבת, Shabbos, I shouldn't have done that,' and
then you forgot again and then you carried again, that defines it
as two separate acts. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yosi omer, now רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi says even בהעלם אחד, be-he'elam echad, even if it's
one state of forgetting, you're not always חייב, chayav, they don't always
combine to form one act. ברשות אחת חייב. Bi-reshus achas chayav. If
you bring them into one domain, into the same public domain, then
we define it as one act. Now תוספות Tosafos by the way
points out that another גמרא Gemara makes it sound like it's not
even enough that it's in the same domain. You have to put
it down in the same place. Right, we could bring it out
to the same Broadway, and we could bring it out like a
mile apart on Broadway. Okay,
but this גמרא Gemara says that it's enough if you bring it
into the same domain. You've brought a minimum amount of food from
a private domain into a public, and it's the same public domain,
even though they were two separate acts and two separate half measures,
that's you're חייב. chayav. בשתי רשויות פטור, Bi-shtei reshuyos patur, if they're
two separate public domains, פטור patur you're exempt. So now according to
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, it becomes interesting to ask what is defined
as two separate public domains. I mean there's obvious cases, like you
know, you've got, but you know, that they're separate from a mile
from one another. But what would be the minimum definition to define
them as separate public domains so you would be exempt if you
brought half an amount into one and half amount into other. So
that's going to be a debate.
Yes, so just to add another aspect to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi,
there were two criteria, which is
quantity...
Well right, meaning I would, I mean the שיעור, shiur, right, is
taken for granted, but what would define combining two half measures would
be the lack of awareness, the continuity of the lack of awareness.
And he says you also need that the act is done in
the same place. Okay? So what is defined as the same place?
דאמר רבה, De'amar Rabba, so רבה Rabba says, והוא שיש חיוב חטאת
ביניהם. vehu sheyesh chiyuv chatat beineihem. To define it as two separate
places, there has to be an obligation of a sin offering between
them, which means a domain which would be defined as a separate
biblical domain that were you to carry into it, you would violate
שבת Shabbat biblically, which means what? רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid.
For biblical purposes of שבת, Shabbat, there's only two domains that matter.
A private domain, which is defined as a space surrounded by four
walls, maybe three, whatever, okay, and a public domain which is a
major thoroughfare. Most of the things out in the world, you know,
outdoors, like, you know, all the homes are private domains, but most
of the things outdoors are neither a private or a public domain,
those are a כרמלית. karmelit. Okay? So if it's not a major
thoroughfare. So for רבה Rabba to say for this private, public domain
to be separated from the other and us to consider them two,
there has to be a private domain between them, so that were
you to carry from one to the other you would transgress biblically
שבת. Shabbat. But if there's just a כרמלית, karmelit, you have two
major thoroughfares and they're combined by, you know, side streets, so those
are not a private domain, but they're not public domains. That is
not enough to separate and that would be considered effectively one public
domain. Okay? So that's what רבה Rabba says. To make it two
so that you would be exempt if you brought half into one
and half into the other, it would only be if there was
a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid between them. אבל כרמלית לא. Aval karmelit
lo. A simple כרמלית, karmelit, something that is neither private nor public,
would not separate those two public domains.
אביי אמר אפילו כרמלית. Abaye amar afilu karmelit. No, even a כרמלית.
karmelit. As long as a public domain ends and something else begins,
and then another public domain begins, that would be two separate public
domains. אבל פיסלא, Aval pisla, if you had a פיסלא, pisla, which
is basically like a type of a raised platform, okay, so you
really had one street, okay, it was one street, but in the
middle of the street you had like, you know, I'm trying to
think of an example, yeah, an island would be a good example,
or like when they have those, you know, those cones in the
middle, what are those called? Not those cones, those pillars, you know,
those plastic pillars they sometimes have to divide a highway or something
like that, right, that might be a good example, okay? So something
like that, right, that's not a separate, that's not even a כרמלית,
karmelit, that doesn't separate it into two public domains. All
right. ורבה אמר אפילו פיסלא. Verabba amar afilu pisla. No, even something
like that, if it demarcates it and physically separates it even if
it's not a different רשות reshut for שבת Shabbat purpose, you know,
it's all within technically the רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, to consider it
two separate acts that you brought half into one and half into
the other and they don't combine to be one act, that is
enough. So that's like רבה's Rabba idea before, that's consistent with what
רבה Rabba said earlier, that a simple like demarcating line divides something
into two domains for שבת Shabbat purposes according to רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi that it matters that we define it as two domains. ואזדא
רבה לטעמיה. Ve'azda Rabba leta'ameih.
רבה Rabba goes according to his reasoning. דאמר רבה רשות שבת כרשות
גיטין
דמי. De'amar Rabba reshut Shabbat kershut Gittin dami. Okay, by שבת, Shabbat,
the idea of separate domains is similar to the idea of גיטין.
Gittin. Now, what does that mean? Where does this matter for גיטין
Gittin purposes?
So
the רשב"ם Rashbam says it's referring to a case in the גמרא
Gemara in גיטין Gittin where a husband, a wife is standing in
a husband's yard and the husband throws the גט get to the
wife. Yeah. And now the sense is that the husband transfers to
the wife ownership of the sort of of the space that she
needs to be קונה koneh her גט. get.
But let's say
that she is not, what do you call it, let's say that
the גט get doesn't fall on the ground, the גט get falls
on a little like platform. So the גמרא Gemara there says then
she's not divorced because he, the husband, we assume is מקנה makneh
one space to her and not two spaces. So he מקנה makneh
to her the space she's standing, but of something that's on a
little platform even though really it's like in the same yard, that
would be considered separate. And since it would be considered separate, it
would not implicitly be included. So therefore that shows this idea that
even something as trivially different as this, like a little platform
on a ground, is considered a separate space and that's relevant for
גיטין. Gittin. רבנו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says it's a different type of
a הלכה, halacha, the הלכה halacha that I think, let me just
double check, I think he says that you have to be עומדת
בצד שדהו, omedet betzad sadehu, one minute,
yeah, he says the הלכה halacha that... That there has to be
היא והגט במקום אחד hi vehaget bemakom echad that you know for
a גט get to work for the ground to work like a
יד yad like an extension of the person, you have to be
standing in the same zone where the גט get falls. So he
says a little different that if it fell on this platform and
she's standing on the ground, it would be considered falling in a
different zone, in a different space. So the same way by גיטין,
Gittin, that's enough of a difference to consider it a different space,
the same would be true for שבת Shabbat purposes. Okay, so that
is sort of wrapping up or revising or revisiting this issue of
when you do a חזקה, Chazakah, is it one plot of land
or two plots of land and looking at it through the lens
of other areas of הלכה. Halacha. Yes.
You mentioned the dried fig. What's the connection between forgetfulness and time
sequence? Like you said if you did it two hours later, you
would not be considered one act.
Right? So what's the memory throughout that whole process?
No, no, no. So by an act of eating, we say it
has to be כדי אכילת פרס. kedei achilat pras. So like if
somebody for example eat, you know sometimes when people have to eat
on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, if there's a question if it's enough
to warrant actually, you know, violating יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, some rabbis
will say you eat like a little less than the amount and
then you wait five minutes or nine minutes and then you eat
another. So for an act of eating, it has to be within
the amount of time it takes to eat a half a loaf
of bread to be considered a continuous act of eating. For this,
it's not the question of the passage of time. It could have
been three hours later. But to be considered one period, it has
to be that the person throughout that period forgot that it was
שבת. Shabbat. And if they remember at any time in between, that
breaks it up as an ongoing process and defines it as two
separate acts. Okay. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this.
Okay. So,
אין שם לא מיצר ולא חצב מאי? ein sham lo meitzar velo
chatzav mai? If there is no boundary marker or no, we'll see
in a minute that חצב chatzav is like some type of a
plant, trees or grass, you know, that define, I guess it's more
of a natural boundary marker that defines the edge of the field,
what would be the הלכה? Halacha? Now, what is this plant? What?
There is... oh that's the name of a plant? Oh okay, what
type of a plant is
it?
It's what those they buy for weddings to make a מחיצה mechitzah
between the men and the women.
You're kidding!
Okay, I thought it was descriptive, you're telling me it's the actual
name of a plant. Great.
I don't know, otherwise I wouldn't have said this, but yeah.
Yeah, yeah, no, no, no, I want to hear, I want to
hear what it is.
It's... I think it was the נודע ביהודה Noda BiYehuda that says
that, and it has a picture in here and I think it's
the same one we mentioned yesterday. Yeah, what? The roots go straight...
I know, we're going to see about that, yeah, yeah, yeah.
The way we're taught, it's called חצב chatzav because it חוצב
באדמה, chotzev ba'adamah,
it's a bulb, and it starts in the fall because when it's
still dry and it
goes straight down,
and then the plant goes straight up.
So that's what we're going to see. Right, we're going to see
that that's going to be a plant that exactly goes straight down
and straight up, so it was planted specifically to serve as a
boundary marker. Okay, so yeah, please let me know what the name
of the plant is. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this.
So, okay, so now what does this mean? What would be the
הלכה Halacha if it was not, if it was not marked? So
the רשב"ם Rashbam says that, let me just double check,
right, how much would you be קונה koneh if you had this
field of נכסי הגר nichsei hager that did not have any clear
marker? So maybe he owned a large big property, how much would
you be קונה koneh if there was no clear marker to demarcate
the edge of it? Now that's a funny question because you could
say if there's no marker to demarcate the edge, you would be
קונה koneh everything, everything that he owns, right, if it's all continuous
property. But maybe the גמרא Gemara for the רשב"ם Rashbam is saying
no, you know, if normally it's defined by conceptually one field, so
what would be that conceptual definition, you know, that definition in the
absence of a marker? So the גמרא Gemara says, so אין שם
לא מיצר ולא חצב מאי? ein sham lo meitzar velo chatzav mai?
So פירש רב מרינוס משמו, peireish Rav Marinus mishmo, so the רשב"ם
Rashbam says it means in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
who was the one who mentioned the statement before, right, about the
מיצר וחצב מפסיקין בנכסי הגר, meitzar vechatzav mafsikin benichsei hager, so he
explained, היכי דמי, heichi dami, so what would it be? מאי? mai?
So פירש רב מרינוס משמו, peireish Rav Marinus mishmo, כל שנקראת על
שמה. kol shenikreit al shemah. Anything that is called by his name.
Anything that the people say oh yeah, all of that belongs to,
you know, to פלוני, Ploni, to ראובן. Reuven. Okay, so if people
recognize it all as his field, that defines the boundaries even if
maybe he owns more, but the extent to which it's all called
one person's field means you do a חזקה Chazakah on a part
of it, you're קונה koneh all of it. Again, if it's הפקר.
hefker.
So, I'll get back to you in a second, okay? So היכי
דמי, heichi dami, what would be the case? אמר רב פפא דקרו
ליה בא גרגוסא דפלניא. Amar Rav Pappa dekaro lei ba gargusa de-planya.
They call it the place of irrigation of so-and-so. גרגוסא Gargusa means,
okay, okay, one second, okay, we're getting back to the חצב, chatzav,
don't worry, okay, where, you know, where so-and-so waters his
field. So for the רשב"ם, Rashbam, in the absence of a boundary
marker, we still have to say when you do a חזקה chazakah
like you turn over a piece of ground, you don't קונה koneh
all the land that the גר ger owns, it would only be
the extent that's considered one unit. And therefore we would define the
unit by the extent to which people recognize it as all belonging
to this person's field. That's the way the רשב"ם Rashbam understands the
question. Again, how much when you do one חזקה chazakah in a
small space, what's the extent to which it's קונה koneh in a
case of a הפקר hefker field. The תוספות Tosfos understands it differently,
if you look at תוספות, Tosfos, אין שם לא מיצר, ein sham
lo meitzar, תוספות Tosfos says אטומא קאי atuma kai כדמוכח בהדיא בתוספתא
דטהרות, kidmucha b'hadya b'Tosefta d'Taharos, דתניא הנכנס לבקעה בימות הגשמים וטומאה בשדה
פלוני. d'tanya hanichnas l'vikah b'yemos hageshamim v'tumah b'sadeh ploni. That this is
going back not to the question of the גר, ger, but to
the question we dealt with yesterday of if you have a doubt
whether you went into the field is it, you know, is it
is it a case of ספק טומאה safek tumah that you're טמא
tamei or ספק טומאה safek tumah that you're טהור? tahor? Can we
say you definitely went into the field and you don't know if
you went over it, or you don't know if you went into
the field, what defines one field or two fields? So then we
would do this definition of כל שנקראת על שמו. kol shenikreis al
shemo. So again, a little unclear whether we're looking back at that
earlier definition of one field or two fields by the גר ger
or this טומאה tumah definition. Okay, now we're going to get back
to this חצב, chatzav, okay, so here we go. יתיב רב אחא
בר אויא קמיה דרבי אסי ויתיב וקאמר משמיה דרבי אסי בר חנינא
חצובא מפסיק בנכסי
הגר. yasiv Rav Acha bar Avya kamei d'Rabbi Assi v'yasiv v'ka'amar mishmeih
d'Rabbi Assi bar Chanina chatzuva mafsik b'nichsei hager.
We've been mentioning this חצב, chatzav, so this חצובא, chatzuva, this plant
divides with נכסי הגר. nichsei hager. מאי חצובא, mai chatzuva, what is
this חצובא? chatzuva? אמר רב יהודה אמר רב שבו תיחם יהושע לישראל
את הארץ, amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav shebo ticham Yehoshua l'Yisrael es
ha'aretz, that's the plant that he used to divide up the land
that it would be very clear, like you know, serve as a
natural boundary of which שבט shevet gets which land and within each
שבט shevet which family gets which land. Okay, and that's the plant
that he used. Now why did he use that plant? So here,
if you look at, I'm getting there, okay, so if you look
at the רשב"ם, Rashbam, שבו תיחם, shebo ticham, he says בין שבט
לשבט בין איש לאיש ולפי שאינו יונק לא מכאן ולא מכאן. bein
shevet l'shevet bein ish l'ish u'lefi she'eino yonek lo mikan v'lo mikan.
So that goes, it went, it goes straight down so it doesn't
spread out in either direction, the roots go straight down, the plant,
the grass or whatever, the plant goes straight up, so it's exactly
as you were saying. Okay, so now what did, you got a
picture for me here? Sea
squill. Okay, so what is it? Sea squill, a plant with a
large bulb that produces green leaves in the winter, dries up completely
during the summer. At the end of the summer it grows a
large inflorescence white flowers, blah blah blah. Its roots are very long
and its bulb is generally planted deep in the earth so that
it's difficult to remove completely. Well that makes sense, if you want
to use it as a boundary marker, you want to make it
hard to remove. Because of its tall straight form that returns annually,
sea squill was used to demarcate boundaries between fields in both ancient
times and even in some Arab villages in the modern era. Okay,
so that's very interesting. Alright, so it says that even until today
that this is used in, apparently not just because it grows straight
up and straight down, but it also says because it's hard to
fully remove.
Okay, and there is a note that it's poisonous.
Oh really? People keep away from it also.
Now you can see in Arab villages the cactuses, right, how cactuses
are like, oh
they use that to create boundaries. Oh, very interesting.
Okay, great, because it won't siphon off the nutrients.
Right, because it goes straight down, right, right, right. Okay, excellent. Alright,
very good.
Alright, so now, now that we're mentioning that יהושע Yehoshua used it
to divide the land, we have a fascinating digression in the גמרא.
Gemara. Let's take a look. ואמר רב יהודה אמר רב, v'amar Rav
Yehuda amar Rav, said רב יהודה Rav Yehuda in the name of
רב, Rav, it's the same רב יהודה אמר רב, Rav Yehuda amar
Rav, so part of the reason we're quoting it is it's same,
it's the same sort of you know person who's saying it, the
same tradition, but also it loosely relates to this point about bounding
off the land, you know, using this plant to create this natural
boundary. לא מנה יהושע אלא עיירות העומדות על הגבולין. lo manah Yehoshua
ela ayaros ha'omdos al hagvulin.
In ספר יהושע Sefer Yehoshua it only listed the cities that were
at the boundary, at the borders, because of you know those are
the relevant cities, you know there's a section in the יהושע Yehoshua
where it lists all the cities they conquered, those are the relevant
cities to know because those are the borders of the land of
ישראל. Yisrael. Of course תוספות Tosfos says that's not true, if you
take a look at תוספות, Tosfos, he says העומדת על הגבולין, ha'omedes
al hagvulin, אין לפרש על הגבולין של ארץ ישראל דכמה עיירות קחשיב
שהם באמצע ארץ ישראל אלא בגבולין דבין שבט לשבט. ein l'faresh al
hagvulin shel Eretz Yisrael d'kama ayaros kachashiv she'hem b'emtza Eretz Yisrael ela
b'gvulin d'bein shevet l'shevet. Right, miss cities there that are in the
middle of ישראל, Yisrael,
it must be that the cities mentioned were the ones that also
similar to this idea of using this plant, right, so you see
the parallel, to mention the cities that are boundary cities, border cities
between various tribes. Okay, very nice. Now אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל,
amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda not in the
name of רב Rav but in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, כל
שהראהו הקדוש ברוך הוא למשה חייב במעשר. kol she'her'ahu Hakadosh Baruch Hu
l'Moshe chayav b'ma'aser. When God shows משה, Moshe, you know, gets to
the end of דברים, Devarim, you know, ויראהו ה' את כל הארץ
את הגלעד. vayar'eihu Hashem es kol ha'aretz es ha'Gilad. עד דן ואת
כל ארץ נפתלי ואת ארץ אפרים ומנשה, ad Dan v'et kol eretz
Naftali v'et eretz Efrayim u-Menasheh, right? So all of that, that is
the land of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael that's חייב במעשר. chayav be-ma'aser.
Okay, לאפוקי מאי, le-appukei mai, what does that exclude? לאפוקי le-appukei קיני
קניזי וקדמוני. Keini, Kenizi, ve-Kadmoni.
So by אברהם, Avraham, if any, when God says to אברהם Avraham
in the ברית בין הבתרים, Brit Bein Habetarim, I'm going to give
you all these lands, it doesn't mention seven Canaanite nations, it mentions
ten. And three of them, the קיני קניזי וקדמוני Keini, Kenizi, ve-Kadmoni
are not mentioned elsewhere when the תורה Torah mentions the seven Canaanite
nations. So the rabbis were sensitive to this and they said what
happened to those three extra lands? So it must be that those
lands are not ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael proper. Now, what does and
therefore they're not חייב במעשר. chayav be-ma'aser. Now, what's the relevance of
this? First of all, the first point תוספות Tosafot makes is, it's
a little funny that the גמרא Gemara points to the vision of
משה, Moshe, because there actually is in the תורה Torah a much
clearer demarcation of the land of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, which is
in the end of במדבר Bamidbar where it says, these are the
גבולות, gevulot, right? And it specifically draws the גבולות. gevulot. So תוספות
Tosafot assumes that they're basically the same. He notes that the גמרא
Gemara really should have said that, that was more specific. Okay, I
don't know why. He doesn't have an answer. But anyway, but let's
talk about what the גמרא Gemara means that the rest is not
חייב בתרומות ומעשר. chayav be-terumot u-ma'aser. So רשב"ם Rashbam says what that
means is, that even if they were to conquer those extra lands,
they would never become incorporated fully into the land of ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael and never be חייב בתרומות ומעשר. chayav be-terumot u-ma'aser. Now,
that might make a certain amount of sense, you know, it could
be land that's owned by
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, but it's not ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael proper.
Like, you know, you think about
these Great Britain, right? It had all these lands that were part
of the empire, but they weren't Great Britain proper. Or Rome, right?
So you could have land that's owned by ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
and not ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael proper and not חייב בתרומות ומעשר.
chayav be-terumot u-ma'aser. The problem is that there's a whole major גמרא
Gemara that discusses the status of סוריא. Surya. סוריא Surya is presumably
some like Syria, some Transjordan area, okay, that because it was conquered,
would be like the land of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and would
be obligated in תרומות ומעשר. terumot u-ma'aser. And the only issue the
גמרא Gemara discusses is that it was כיבוש יחיד. kibbush yachid. It
was privately conquered. Now what does privately conquered mean? So some say
it means that דוד David did it without getting specific license from
the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, or some say that דוד David did it because
he did it before he conquered ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael proper. But
the point is that everybody there agrees that if it was כיבוש
רבים, kibbush rabbim, if it was done in the proper way, it
would be incorporated into ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and it would actually
be חייב בתרומות ומעשר. chayav be-terumot u-ma'aser. So the רשב"ם Rashbam seems
to say, okay, maybe those are the lands that are immediately, immediately
juxtaposed, immediately contiguous with ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Those could be incorporated.
But let's say ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael were to go to war
and to conquer, you know, France, okay? So it would be a
כיבוש רבים. kibbush rabbim. It would be done with the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin,
it would be after they conquered ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael proper, would
that be חייב בתרומות ומעשר? chayav be-terumot u-ma'aser? Maybe certain lands, even
with the idea of כיבוש רבים, kibbush rabbim, are so distant that
they never become incorporated into ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael proper. So that's
what the רשב"ם Rashbam said is being said here. That these lands
of קיני קניזי וקדמוני, Keini, Kenizi, ve-Kadmoni, which is fascinating, because it's
part of what God promised אברהם. Avraham. So even though it's part
of what God promised אברהם, Avraham, says the רשב"ם, Rashbam, even when
you conquer it, it's not part of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael proper.
It's not חייב בתרומות ומעשר. chayav be-terumot u-ma'aser.
Is it because it's so far away?
Maybe, he doesn't say why. Because because it's never because when the
תורה Torah repeats what you're going to get, it only says the
seven Canaanite nations. And in במדבר Bamidbar it says this is the
land that I promised, you know, אשר נשבעתי לאבותם, asher nishbati la'avotam,
so it's only those that. This is some type of messianic vision,
and because it's some messianic future vision and it's not the real
promised land, therefore even when you conquer it, he says, it is
not part of. Yeah, המילי, ha-milei, let's read the רשב"ם Rashbam together.
He says,
he says like this, חייב במעשר, chayav be-ma'aser, so it's a line
תוספות Tosafot במעשר, be-ma'aser, it's about 10 lines before the משנה, Mishnah,
דהם הם זיין עממים הכתובים בכל מקום. de-hein hein zayin amamim ha-ketuvim
be-khol makom. אבל קיני קניזי וקדמוני שנתנו לאברהם אבינו בין הבתרים
ראוי להתחייב במעשר לעתיד לבוא, Aval Keini, Kenizi, ve-Kadmoni, she-natnu le-Avraham Avinu
bein habetarim, ra'uy l'hit-chayev be-ma'aser le-atid lavo, even in the future when
שיחזירו לנו לעתיד. she-yachziru lanu le-atid. So they're they're we believe
we deserve them, they're coming back to us, we're going to get
them. Even though they're promised and we're going to get them, they're
still not ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael proper. דאמר בבראשית רבה אי נמי
אם כבשו ישראל מהם אחרי מות יהושע כולם פטורים מן המעשר. Te-emar
be-Bereishit Rabbah, i-nami im kibshu Yisrael me-hem acharei mot Yehoshua, kulam peturim
min ha-ma'aser. דכתיב התם זאת הארץ שנשבעתי זאת למעוטי הני שנמסרו לאברהם
על השבועה. Dikhtiv hatam zot ha'aretz she-nishbati, zot le-ma'utei hanei she-nimsru le-Avraham
al hashvuah. These were extra. This is not the עיקר ikar land
that was promised with a שבועה. shevuah. This was some future promise.
And the amazing thing is that even though there's סוגיות sugyas in
the גמרא Gemara about כיבוש רבים kibbush rabbim becomes part of ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, this presumably is too distant that it doesn't become
it even though it was promised.
It would need to be
closer because it was promised. I know, but he must imagine that
it's further away than סוריא. Surya. סוריא Surya because the גמרא Gemara
thinks that סוריא Surya could be חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות. terumos
u'maasros. So that's the רשב"ם, Rashbam, pretty wild idea. תוספות Tosafos makes
this a little bit, tames this down a little bit. תוספות Tosafos
says no, no, no. All what the גמרא Gemara means is that
תוספות Tosafos makes this sort of not saying anything that new. תוספות
Tosafos says this גמרא Gemara is assuming
קדושה ראשונה קדשה לשעתה וקדשה לעתיד לבוא. kdusha rishona kidsha l'shaata v'kidsha
l'asid lavo. What defined the land of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisroel to
be obligated in תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'maasros goes by what they conquered
in the time of יהושע Yehoshua and not by what they conquered
in later generations. So even if they conquer more in later generations,
it's all defined by the time of יהושע. Yehoshua. And therefore all
that this is really saying is that these lands were not conquered
in the time of יהושע. Yehoshua. Okay, so then it's not really
such an interesting statement because we sort of knew that they weren't
conquered in the time of יהושע. Yehoshua.
Okay, what about what דוד Dovid in סוריא? Surya?
So that גמרא Gemara presumably understands קדושה שנייה קדשה לשעתה וקדשה לעתיד
לבוא. kdusha shniya kidsha l'shaata v'kidsha l'asid lavo. The discussions of סוריא
Surya of כיבוש רבים. kibush rabim. Okay, but the, but this discussion,
oh you're right, I'm sorry. שנייה shniya you're right is the time
of עזרא. Ezra. Right. דוד, Dovid, yeah, that's a good question in
general, like that must understand that the קדושה ראשונה kdusha rishona probably
continues through the end of the בית ראשון Bayis Rishon period. You're
right, it's like it doesn't end with יהושע. Yehoshua. I mean that's
in general that question of that discussion of סוריא, Surya, right? Because
is it assuming קדושה ראשונה kdusha rishona or קדושה שנייה? kdusha shniya?
It seems like so yes, but the, but even so let's take
a look at תוספות, Tosafos, okay? Let's read תוספות. Tosafos. חייב במעשר.
chayav b'maaser. ואם תאמר וכולהו Ve'im tomar ve'chulhu is this a general
rule? והלא הרבה כרכים כבשום עולי מצרים ולא כבשום עולי בבל ולא
נתחייבו במעשר אף על פי שהראם למשה. Ve'halo harbei krachim kivshum olei
Mitzrayim v'lo kivshum olei Bavel v'lo nis'chayvu b'maaser af al pi she'heram
l'Moshe. He says anyway you go by, you go by what happens
in the time of עזרא Ezra when that defines it. יש אומרים
דקסבר קדושה ראשונה קדשה לשעתה וקדשה לעתיד לבוא. Yesh omrim d'kasvar kdusha
rishona kidsha l'shaata v'kidsha l'asid lavo. והא דניחא ליה שלא תקשה כל
אותן עיירות וכל אותן כרכים שכבשום עולי מצרים ולא כבשום עולי בבל.
Ve'ha d'nicha lei shelo tikshe kol osan ayayaros v'kol osan krachim shekivshum
olei Mitzrayim v'lo kivshum olei Bavel. Okay because he basically according to
תוספות Tosafos all it's saying is is that the whole land conquered
by יהושע Yehoshua is holy and not the land promised to אברהם.
Avraham. So according to תוספות Tosafos all that it's saying is is
that don't think, and this is actually an interesting point, right? It's
the difference between the divine promise and the reality. Don't think ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisroel for תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'maasros is defined by the
divine promise. Even if God promised it to אברהם, Avraham, that is
not what defines ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisroel. What defines ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisroel is the reality of what they conquered. And since they didn't
conquer those lands, therefore they do not have קדושה kdusha for תרומות
ומעשרות. terumos u'maasros. Okay. By the way though, it raises an interesting
question because it, I don't, like I said that's a good question.
Maybe, so maybe that's a question about, you know, they did conquer
סוריא, Surya, they didn't conquer these lands. But I'll tell you the
interesting question here because the question
is what, what is the point anyway about the boundaries? And now
you're going to see my, my terrible drawing of ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisroel. Okay, well that's actually מדבר סיני. Midbar Sinai. Okay, anyway, so
these boundaries have been
here for thousands of years. Yes.
Well, well yeah, meaning what do you mean? אברהם Avraham and then
what it says in במדבר. Bamidbar. Yeah. So that's what exactly what
it's dealing with. Okay. What is the relevance of the boundaries that
the תורה Torah draws? If the issue in the גמרא Gemara is
that קדושה ראשונה kdusha rishona you go by what was conquered by
יהושע, Yehoshua, why does the תורה Torah tell us boundaries? I mean
let's just see what יהושע Yehoshua conquered. So maybe it's sort of
telling you what you're expected to get and what you should try
to conquer when you go in the land and they didn't always
finish conquering everything. So you know, maybe it's not to tell you
this is what is קדוש, kadosh, but this is what I'm giving
you and this is what you have to try to conquer. But
is there a relevance for the boundaries in במדבר Bamidbar for this
הלכה halacha of תרומות ומעשרות? terumos u'maasros? So if the גמרא Gemara
says קדושה ראשונה קדשה לשעתה, kdusha rishona kidsha l'shaata, it goes by
what they conquered in the time of יהושע. Yehoshua. And those are
עולי מצרים. olei Mitzrayim. So the question I have is let's say
what they conquered in the time of יהושע, Yehoshua, right? Let's say
they conquered the main, just specifically what they didn't, exactly, let's say
they conquered like you know this and this and this and maybe
they had a little problem here with עזה, Gaza, you know, and
they conquered this. So but the boundaries were given like this. Does
the fact that you look at it as one unit and you
say they basically conquered it, right? There's some areas they have to
finish up, but they basically conquered it means that it all has
קדושה? kdusha? You don't measure inch by inch and mile by mile
that oh this little piece they didn't conquer that that's not חייב.
chayav. No you don't say that, you say these are the boundaries,
they basically conquered the land, the rest is mop up stuff and
therefore it's all חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות. terumos u'maasros. So I
think that it works in some combination of the two. So exactly
like that. So what the גמרא Gemara is saying is is if
this is the שבע עממין sheva amamin and over here is קיני
קניזי וקדמוני, Keni Knizi v'Kadmoni, let's even assume that it's attached, okay,
you don't say that just because they conquered this that this has
קדושה. kdusha. This is distinct. So that's what תוספות Tosafos is saying.
The point of this is is we're going by the קדושה ראשונה,
kdusha rishona, we're going by what יהושע... Yehoshua... conquered, and that works
for the land, even if it wasn't 100% that was, that משה
Moshe saw, the land that was drawn out in במדבר. Bamidbar. It
does not work for the land over here.
Okay.
That's what you just said. Yes. So in the times of the
מלחמות Milchamot against the פלשתים Plishtim in the time of דוד המלך.
David HaMelech. Right. שאול. Shaul. So עקרון Ekron and גת Gat and
all those lands. Right. פלשתים, Plishtim, according to this, they would have
קדושה. Kedusha.
Yes, and that's what Michael's asking too, right? How long do you
view this just as יהושע Yehoshua or as an ongoing process during
the entire בית ראשון Bayit Rishon period? The גמרא's Gemara discussion about
סוריא, Surya, which was conquered by David, sounds like you look at
this as an ongoing process. Okay, but lands that are outside of
these boundaries, it would only go by exactly what was conquered. All
right, so and just saying you got this doesn't automatically bring in
other lands.
Conceptually, I totally get what you're saying and how it's reflected in
תוספות, Tosafot, for example. What, why was there a question, for example,
with בית שאן? Beit She'an? בית שאן, Beit She'an, that's בית שני.
Bayit Sheni. So that assumes that you don't go by the time
of יהושע, Yehoshua, you go by the time of עזרא. Ezra. And
then the question is, did they resanctify it and resettle it in
the time of עזרא? Ezra? So that's the fundamental... Yeah, there's a
major debate whether you go by the time of יהושע Yehoshua or
the time of עזרא. Ezra.
But according to both רשב"ם Rashbam and תוספות, Tosafot, even if you
would conquer קיני קניזי וקדמוני, Keni Knizi VeKadmoni, it would be, the
גמרא Gemara says לאפוקי. Le'appukei.
Right, but according to תוספות, Tosafot, that might mean assuming we're going
by קדושה ראשונה, Kedusha Rishona, what they conquered in the time of
יהושע Yehoshua doesn't have relevance for קיני קניזי וקדמוני. Keni Knizi VeKadmoni.
תוספות Tosafot is not excluding the possibility that if they actually were
to conquer קיני קניזי וקדמוני, Keni Knizi VeKadmoni, it might actually be
קדוש, Kadosh, especially if you go by קדושה שנייה. Kedusha Sheniya. Okay?
He's just saying the conquering of יהושע Yehoshua doesn't automatically שלעפ shlep
in the status of קיני קניזי וקדמוני. Keni Knizi VeKadmoni. All right,
but that's assuming קדושה ראשונה. Kedusha Rishona. If you went קדושה שנייה,
Kedusha Sheniya, it would be different. All right, so now the גמרא
Gemara says what are these lands. Okay, so תניא, Tanya, Rabbi Meir
אומר: omer: נבטייא, Navtiya, ערביא, Arviya, and שלמייא, Shalmiya, I guess. So
I don't know, what does it say there? נבטייא, Navtiya, what
does it say the lands are? I mean, ערביא's Arviya probably Arabia,
right? What, what? It doesn't give you the English there? Okay, those
are the lands he identifies. You'll tell us in a minute. Rabbi
Yehuda אומר: omer: הר שעיר עמון ומואב. Har Seir Amon VeMoav. Now
that makes sense. Those are the lands that actually... that's a fascinating
read because those are the lands that immediately border ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. And not only do they immediately border ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
what's significant about those lands? הר שעיר עמון ומואב? Har Seir Amon
VeMoav?
Those
are עשו Esav and לוט, Lot, right? Exactly. So those are the
lands that בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael are told: Do not conquer it,
כי ירושה נתתי את לעשו, ki yerusha natati et le'Esav, right? So
it's a fascinating read. אברהם Avraham gets promised—think about this a minute—אברהם
Avraham gets promised קיני קניזי וקדמוני. Keni Knizi VeKadmoni. You know, they
actually do go to אברהם's Avraham children, or אברהם's Avraham family. Who
do they go to? לוט Lot and עשו, Esav, which are part
of אברהם's Avraham family. Just not you. Just not בני ישראל. Bnei
Yisrael. He has a covenant with them.
Exactly.
So that is like an amazing read of the פסוקים. pesukim. What
happened to those three nations? They did go to אברהם's Avraham family,
just not the Jewish part of אברהם's Avraham family. They went to
these, right? And because they've been sort of given to those, you
don't have rights to them. So that's like an amazing read. Rabbi
Shimon אומר: omer: ארדיסקוס, Ardiscus, אסייא, Asya, and אספמיא. Aspamya. So אסייא
Asya is apparently Asia. Now אספמיא, Aspamya, when we had it before,
I read it as Spain. That was a completely wrong read, because
I check and at least, what do you call it, Soncino says
it's a name of some, of some other country in Asia. It
is not Spain. What does this say?
אספמיא Aspamya refers to Northern Syria.
Northern Syria. And what's... what's ארדיסקוס? Ardiscus?
All these are places in Asia Minor.
Asia Minor. Okay. And what were the other ones? What were נבטייא
ערביא ושלמייא? Navtiya Arviya VeShalmiya?
Well, he says no, here he says these are places that are
mentioned like Nabatean nations, and he skips them.
But he's saying that these lands situated south of ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael from the Dead Sea to אילת. Eilat. South, really?
That's what he said, the first group.
The first group of נבטייא ערביא
ושלמייא.
Navtiya
Arviya VeShalmiya.
Oh, really? Somewhere here? Somewhere, somewhere in... in Egypt?
No, it says south of the Dead Sea.
Dead Sea to אילת. Eilat. Southern portion of Eastern Transjordan extending to
Northern Arabia.
Huh. But Asia is over here. Asia Minor, right?
So these are three different opinions.
Three different opinions. Okay, very interesting.
Does that mean that like, let's say, conceptually, halachically, like there's a
question let's say about אילת, Eilat, do they keep... Yeah.
But part of that has to go with קדושה ראשונה, Kedusha Rishona,
קדושה שנייה, Kedusha Sheniya, it all has to depend. Okay, let's go.
Next משנה. Mishna.
He forgot to mention אילת Eilat as עציון גבר. Etzion Gever.
Right. But that's part of the question. Do you go by קדושה
ראשונה? Kedusha Rishona? Do you... there are three realities. I mean, there's
more. There's what... well, first of all, there's what אברהם Avraham was
promised. That's what we're discussing. But there's what the תורה Torah says
when it draws the boundaries in במדבר. Bamidbar. There's what they actually
conquered in the time of יהושע. Yehoshua. And then there's what they
settled in when they returned in the time of עזרא. Ezra. Now
there's actually more realities because in the time of יהושע, Yehoshua, it
continued through the time of David. In the time of עזרא, Ezra,
it continued through the time of the חשמונאים, Chashmonaim, right? So there's
a lot of different... things you could look at. Let's take a
look at the משנה. Mishnah. היו, Hayu, so that was a fascinating
little digression. Back to standard
בבא בתרא Bava Batra issues. היו שנים עדים שאכלה שלש שנים. Hayu
shnayim edim she-achlah shalosh shanim. Okay, so now we get some מכות
Makkot stuff. Okay, so three, two people said you were here for
three years and they said that David was on my land for
three years and it was going to be awarded to David, and
then it was found out that they were all lying, that they
were all with somebody else in a different place, classic עדים זוממים,
edim zomemim, so they were trying to make me lose my land,
they have to pay me for, you know, the value of the
land. משלמים לו את הכל. Meshalmim lo et hakol. They pay me
the full value. Now, שנים בראשונה ושנים בשנייה ושנים בשלישית. Shnayim barishonah
ushnayim bashniyah ushnayim bashlishit. Let's say David brings three sets of עדים.
edim. You know, the first set says David ate year one, the
second year two, the third year three, and they were all turned
out זוממים. zomemim. משלשין ביניהם. Meshaleshin beneihem. Then you divide it, each
one of those groups of עדים edim pays the third of the
value of the land. Right, because they did it all together. Now,
two points. Number one is this phrase משלשין ביניהם meshaleshin beneihem is
used in the גמרא Gemara in מכות Makkot to say exactly this,
that the עדים edim have to sort of divide it, if there's
multiple עדים edim they divide the obligations between them. But you know,
one of the questions asked in מכות Makkot is why does it
use the word משלשין meshaleshin which is from the root of שלוש?
shalosh? So you divide it into three. So it might be that
this is the root of it because this is the original version
where there's three groups on three separate years. So it says you
divide it into thirds. And then it's used as a sort of
metaphoric to just mean you divide it proportional to the amount of
people that were involved. No,
no, no. They use משלשין meshaleshin for a... no, that's not the
context. For עדים זוממים edim zomemim that you divide the monetary obligation
between them.
Now, number two is תוספות Tosafot asks a question. תוספות Tosafot says,
why can't the first two groups of עדים edim say, we weren't
trying to award the field to David, we weren't trying to steal
it from Dov, we were actually testifying that David ate Dov's grain,
you know, illegally for that year and we were trying to help
out Dov? We weren't trying to help out David. So even if
we were lying, you know, who knows, maybe we owe the cost
of that year of grain to David, but we don't owe the
cost of the field to Dov, right? How do you know what
they were coming for? So תוספות Tosafot says it depends who brought
the עדים. edim. Okay, if David brought the עדים edim and he
brought all three groups together, clearly you look at them as one
big unit and they're all coming to take the field away from
me. And if they're all lying, you divide it among them.
And that's ששה עדים זוממים. shishah edim zomemim.
Six עדים זוממים. edim zomemim. Now, שלשה אחים ואחד מצטרף עמהם. Sheloshah
achim ve-echad mitztaref imahem. Let's say those three groups were actually made
up of three brothers, ראובן, שמעון ולוי. Reuven, Shimon ve-Levi. ראובן Reuven
testified to year one, שמעון Shimon testified to year two, לוי Levi
testified to year three. ואחד מצטרף עמהם. Ve-echad mitztaref imahem. And then
you had some fourth guy, מרדכי, Mordechai, who was unrelated, and he
saw all three years. So group number one was ראובן ומרדכי, Reuven
u-Mordechai, group number two was שמעון ומרדכי, Shimon u-Mordechai, and group number
three was לוי ומרדכי. Levi u-Mordechai. Okay, so does that work? So
the משנה Mishnah says, הרי אלו שלש עדויות. harei elu shalosh eduyot.
So those are three separate testimonies. It's not like you say, oh,
brothers can't testify on the same thing. Because each year is a
distinct year, it's not considered to be like two brothers are testifying
on the same thing. One brother's testifying on year one and one
on year two, so they're distinct, so that works. But ואין עדות
אחת להזמה. ve-ein edut achat lehazamah. When it comes to the idea
that if they're all turned out to be lying, then you view
them as all combined working to achieve one thing, to award David
the חזקה. chazakah. And therefore, they all have to be... you know,
nobody pays as עדים זוממים edim zomemim until it turns out like
that they're all lying. So they're seen as one big set of
facts if you will, for הזמה hazamah purposes, because together they all
achieve one thing. But it's not one עדות edut and therefore it
doesn't matter that there's one brother on one year and one brother
on another year.
Yeah, doesn't matter what they actually saw mean, like let's say all
three of them really did see him three years, but just, you
know, since he actually needs to have it הלכתית halachically acceptable, so
you could have said you first year, second year, or third year
and, you know, like leave out one of the brothers. But then
he brought this מרדכי Mordechai and so it happens to be that
officially מרדכי
ושמעון... Mordechai ve-Shimon... ראובן Reuven says year one, then מרדכי Mordechai and
then שמעון Shimon says year two.
Although they could have gone in any order. Right, that's a good
point. If all three of them saw all three years, you might
then sort of coach them to only testify on one year each
so you don't have an issue with the brothers. That's a good
point, yes, and that would be fine. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. מתניתין, Matnitin, thank God, excuse me for saying that,
we're not going to get into עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, okay? We're
getting into so many different things. We're going to focus on one
particular aspect of this משנה. Mishnah. מתניתין Matnitin דלא כרבי עקיבא. dela
ke-Rabbi Akiva.
It's not going like Rabbi Akiva. דתניא. Detanya. אמר רבי יוסי, Amar
Rabbi Yosi, כששלח אבא חלפתא אצל רבי יוחנן בן נורי Kesheshalach Abba
Chalafta etzel Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri when אבא חלפתא Abba Chalafta who
was apparently his father, this is רבי יוסי בן חלפתא, Rabbi Yosi
ben Chalafta, when he went to רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan
ben Nuri ללמוד תורה, lilmod Torah, to learn Torah. ואמרי לה, Ve-amrei
lah, רבי יוחנן בן נורי אצל אבא חלפתא ללמוד תורה. Rabbi Yochanan
ben Nuri etzel Abba Chalafta lilmod Torah. I love this. They don't
know who was the רבי Rebbi and who was the student, okay?
So I guess they were pretty מתקלי. matkali. Anyway, so one went
to the other. to learn ללמוד תורה *lilmod Torah*. אמר לו *Amar
lo*. So whoever went said to the other one: הרי שאכלה שנה
ראשונה בפני שנים, שניה בפני שנים, שלישית בפני שנים, מהו *Harei she'achla
shanah rishonah bifnei shenayim, sheniyah bifnei shenayim, shelishis bifnei shenayim, mahu*? So,
you know, we're finally asking, I mean, it's such a big of
a question, right? How do you bring proof that you've had a
חזקה chazaka *chazakah*? Who's going to witness you on there continuously for
three years? So let's say you have one group of עדים *edim*
that witness year one, one group that witness year two, one group
that witness year three, forget עדים זוממים *edim zomemim*. Do they all
combine? What's the story, מהו *mahu*? So אמר לו *amar lo*, הרי
זו חזקה chazaka *harei zo chazakah*, they combine. אמר לו *amar lo*,
אף אני אומר כן *af ani omer kein*. You know, I think
so too. אלא שרבי עקיבא חולק בדבר *Ella she'Rabbi Akiva cholek badavar*,
but רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* thinks it doesn't work. Why? שהיה רבי
עקיבא אומר *she'haya Rabbi Akiva omer*, דבר *davar*, על פי שנים עדים
יקום דבר *al pi shenayim edim yakum davar*, ולא חצי דבר *velo
chatzi davar*, not half. So since any one year is does not
is not the full statement of חזקה chazaka *chazakah*, you could even
go further. Any one year proves the opposite of חזקה chazaka. *chazakah*.
One year that David is eating on my field proves that David
owes me a year of my grain. So but certainly and the
one testimony is not a is a partial חזקה chazaka? *chazakah*. It
is not a full חזקה chazaka *chazakah*. And you need that עדים
*edim* testify to a full matter. And he says they don't combine.
Okay, so that's a very high demand. Very hard to get עדות
edut *edus* according to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*. Okay, ורבנן האי דבר
ולא חצי דבר מאי עביד ליה *ve'Rabbanan hai davar velo chatzi davar
mai avidlei*. Now for the Rabbis, they the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes
that the Rabbis would agree that you can't have testimony on a
half matter. But this is not considered a half matter. What would
be considered a half matter for the Rabbis? אילימא למעוטי *Ileima lim'utei*
אחד אומר בגבה אחת בגבה ואחד אומר אחת בכרסה *echad omer begava
achas begava ve'echad omer achas be'kreisa*. So this is the question of
testifying that a girl is has reached puberty and is considered an
adult. So it is actually, I mean, this is a, you know,
it's a uncomfortable גמרא Gemara's *Gemara* because it talks about like two
strangers because the father can't testify, men looking at her pubic hair
and identifying that she has two pubic hairs. Okay, so and two
see that she has one in the, you know, sort of from
a front view and the other see a different one from the
back view. Okay, so in that type of a case maybe the
two testimonies can't combine. So so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, I'm
sorry, no, first we said one. One witness sees the front view
and one sees the back view. אחד אומר בגבה *echad omer begava*.
So so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אחד אומר בגבה ואחד אומר
בכרסה *echad omer begava ve'echad omer be'kreisa*, האי חצי דבר וחצי עדות
edut היא *hai chatzi davar ve'chatzi edus hi*. That's not just a
half of a two, you know, two testimonies can't combine. When we
say two testimonies can't combine, it means as if you have two
witnesses for half A and two witnesses for half B and they
don't combine. In this case, you have one witness for half A
and one witness for half B, right? You understand the difference? You
don't even start with a full set of witnesses on anything. So
that obviously is not true. It doesn't even need a פסוק *pasuk*.
אלא למעוטי שנים אומרין בגבה ושנים אומרין בכרסה *Ella lim'utei shenayim omrin
begava veshenayim omrin be'kreisa*. Two say they saw a pubic hair from
the back and two say they saw it from the front. And
in that case they can't combine. Now, why is that different than
one year, one year, and one year? So the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam*
and תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* have two explanations. The רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* says
because one year, one year, and one year, when you're witnessing the
one year, you can't see year two. You've seen everything there is
to see during year one. Okay, so that's not a חצי דבר
*chatzi davar*. But if you were standing there with the girl and
you could have gotten the whole information and you only got half
the information, then that's a חצי דבר *chatzi davar* because you could
have seen everything. Okay, and therefore, the fact that you had all
of that information available to be seen and you only saw half
that was relevant, that's חצי דבר *chatzi davar*. That's the way the
רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* explains it. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* says it has nothing
to do with that. I don't care if you could have seen
more, you couldn't have seen more. What תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* says is
the difference is is that when you testify to one year, it's
like what I said before. That testimony would be meaningful by itself
in a different context. How would the testimony that David ate a
year of my grain be meaningful even if it were not a
חזקה chazaka. *chazakah* testimony? I told you before. How's it relevant? Then
then you'd have to pay me back. So since that testimony could
stand independently to serve a different purpose, it's considered a full דבר
*davar*. Okay, and therefore can combine with two other years to make
three years. The testimony of one pubic hair is meaningless. It doesn't
serve anybody any purpose in הלכה *halacha*. And therefore, it doesn't combine,
it doesn't stand alone to combine with other things. Okay, so everybody
agrees that it needs to be full, but רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*'s
definition of full is very demanding. It has to be the total
testimony of the. All right. Now, אמר רב יהודה *Amar Rav Yehuda*,
now here's another interesting application of this question of a full or
partial testimony.
אחד אומר אכלה חטים ואחד אומר אכלה שעורים הרי זו חזקה chazaka?
*Echad omer achla chittim ve'echad omer achla se'orim, harei zo chazakah*. One
set of witnesses say that they that you
ate for three years grain,
and another set of witnesses say,
no, I mean wheat, and another says, no, you ate those three
years but you weren't eating wheat, you were eating barley. So he's...
One witness, one witness. Right, you're right because we're combining it to
be two witnesses. Thank you. Okay, one witness says, thank you, you
ate three years of wheat and one witness says that
you ate three years of barley. הרי זו חזקה, chazakah that combines.
Now why does it combine? So one way of understanding why it
combines is because sometimes we abstract, particularly if you're dealing with דיני
ממונות. dinei mamonot. So let's say Michael here says I
borrowed $100 from Michal and David says I didn't see whether Dov
borrowed $100 from Michal but what I did see is that
Dov
promised her or whatever damaged her property and owes her $100 for
that purpose. Okay so maybe that's a little bit of an extreme
because it's a damage and a borrow but whatever. Or Michal gave
Dov $100 that he now has to give it back. So both
of you if we abstract a little bit if we say concretely
are you testifying that the same act took place? No. But if
we abstract you're both saying that I owe her $100. So there
actually is an opinion in the גמרא Gemara that we combine your
testimonies and say I owe her $100 because you're saying I owe
her $100 and you're saying I owe her $100 for totally different
reasons but we combine them to say I owe her $100. What?
I know. So there's a debate about that. So the רשב"ם Rashbam
says that's what we might be saying here. You say I have
three years of חזקה chazakah? for eating wheat for three years. You
say I have three years of חזקה for eating barley for three
years. You're not testifying to the same thing but each of you
if we abstract it are saying that I have חזקה so we'll
combine it to say there's עדות edut that I have חזקה. Yes
Michal. Okay so
so that's the question that's the claim. So מתיב ליה רב נחמן.
metiv leh Rav Nachman. So רב נחמן Rav Nachman asks about this.
אלא מעתה אחד אומר אכלה ראשונה שלישית וחמישית ואחד אומר אכלה שניה
רביעית ושישית הכי נמי דהוי חזקה? Ela me-ata echad omer achlah rishona
shelishit ve-chamishit ve-echad omer achlah shniya reviit ve-shishit hachi nami de-havya chazaka?
So if one said you ate years one, three, and five and
the other said you ate years two, four, and six, are you
going to say that that's a חזקה? Now that combines? Now the
question is wait that's different. If they're not continuous neither עדות is
testifying that you had a חזקה like saying discontinuous years are not
a חזקה. So תוספות Tosfos says no no no we mean that
presumably there's times when if you have discontinuous it is. Remember if
you let it lay fallow because that's the normal thing is to
let it lay fallow in the intermediate years. So תוספות is just
saying that what the גמרא's Gemara real pushback is: Can you really
say that testimony that contradicts itself combines for a חזקה? Okay because
in this case all right if I say if Michael says I
borrowed $100 from Michal and David says she whatever she gave me
$100 of her to watch or something of that nature you're not
contradicting one another. You're not saying the same thing but you're not
contradicting one another. But if you say three years of wheat and
you say three years of barley or you say years one, three,
and five I harvested and two, four, and six it was fallow
and you say the reverse you're contradicting! So it's very different to
say that we can abstract and combine to say that when they
contradict we can combine. So how does this work?
So the גמרא Gemara says: you mean when he says two, four,
and six it's to the exclusion of one, three, and five? Yeah
that's the way תוספות is reading it. Not just I didn't happen
to see. Right exactly. רשב"ם Rashbam, has a different read which I'll
tell you in a minute. So it says: אמר ליה רב יהודה
הכי השתא. amar leh Rav Yehuda hachi hashta. What type of comparison
is that? התם בשעתא דקמסהיד מר לא קמסהיד מר. hatam beshata de-ka-mashid
mar lo ka-mashid mar.
Here they're not saying the same year. Now that sounds not like
contradicting but they're not talking about the same thing. Maybe you don't
even have to contradict. They're not even testifying about the same years.
You're saying not two, four, and six?
Yes but no but the way the גמרא Gemara reads now is
it seems
to say even without saying explicitly what happened in the intermediate years.
Okay but הכא תרוייהו בחד שתא קמסהדי. hacha tarvaihu be-chad shata ka-mashadi.
Here
they're both testifying the same three years. Okay but you're contradicting. One
says wheat and one says barley. So מאי איכא למימר? mai ika
le-meimar? What is bothering you? בין חיטי לשערי לאו אדעתיה דאינשי. bein
chiti le-se'ari lav adatei de-inshei.
So you know what? So okay one said wheat one said barley.
People don't pay attention. Who knows the difference between? Right exactly. If
it was wheat and vegetables, wheat and fruit then it wouldn't combine.
Okay so the way in the end what's clear in the end
is that the גמרא Gemara. says it works when it's a type
of a normal mistake and the גמרא Gemara. has these other types
by עדות that we say people were like imprecise and they that's
not really a contradiction. What's left open is the question of is
it similar to the case of each of you say I owe
Michal. Hundred dollars for a different reason, right? So if you actually
say, right, that I have what if you have that case where
you were not you know it sounds like according to the way
תוספות reads the conclusion, that it doesn't work in the same way.
If you say years one, three, and five, and he says two,
four, and six, and you don't know what happened in the end
in the other years and he doesn't know what happened in the
other years, it still seems like we wouldn't say well or let's
say easier you say years one, two, and three, a straight continuous
חזקה and you don't know what happened after and David says years
four, five, and six and he doesn't know what happened before. Would
we combine those to say חזקה? Right? Or would we not? Would
that be like saying I borrowed a hundred dollars or you know
I owe a hundred dollars for a different reason? So that's left
as an open question. At the end of the day, what we
know is the reason it combines here is because we're saying they
really are saying exactly the same thing, they just got the details
mixed up. But how much can we abstract and combine is not
clear. Now by the way I do want to just point out
one brief point, which is the רשב"ם's reading of it is I
don't want to go through the whole way the רשב"ם reads it,
but he reads that the testimony about wheat and barley was that
actually
just like the גמרא says later, that you were saying years one,
three, and five were wheat and the other guy was saying two,
four, and six were barley, and they were actually saying that. And
the question and the issue is in that case, right, is that
considered so if you look at the רשב"ם, I just want to
point out that it's very if you take a look here it's
very interesting because he actually did some research. Okay, he said,
it's three lines before the lines get wide. אחד אומר אכלן חטין
ג' שנים כפי מנהג עובדי האדמה ואחד אומר אכלן שעורין ג' שנים
כפי מנהג עובדי האדמה והיינו שש שנים בדילוג. Echad omer achlan chittin
gimmel shanim k'fi min'hag ovdei ha'adama v'echad omer achlan se'orim gimmel shanim
k'fi min'hag ovdei ha'adama v'hainu shesh shanim b'dilug. And then he says
ושאלתי לעובדי האדמה. v'sha'alti l'ovdei ha'adama. I went and I did some
research, I asked actual some
farmers ואמרו לי שלעולם כך הוא המנהג. v'amru li shele'olam kach hu
haminhag. שנה אחת חטין ושנה אחת שעורין. Shana achas chittin v'shana achas
se'orim. They do rotation of crops, right?
וכל ימי ואין צריך שביתה כלל V'chol kol yami v'ein tzarich shevvisa
klal and you don't have to let it lay fallow if you
rotate the crops. הרי זו חזקה שאין הם מכחישים זה את זה
כלל. Harei zo chazakah she'ein heim mach-chishim zeh es zeh klal. So
they're not contradicting because it's basically just a normal thing to overturn
it. So he has his own way of reading the גמרא which
I don't want to go into, but I just thought it was
interesting that he actually did a little research and went out and
asked people, hey how does it work? Okay, and then he sort
of says that's פשט pshat in the גמרא. But at the end
of the day, the reason this combines is because they ממש mamash
said that they got the details mixed up, but they are actually
saying the exact same thing. Could we actually abstract if Michael says
one, two, and three and David says four, five, and six, can
we combine that? That never is fully answered in the גמרא. Okay,
so we'll pick up with this tomorrow.